<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reference on jrem.me - wonder.explore.share</title>
    <link>/tags/reference/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reference on jrem.me - wonder.explore.share</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Jul 2021 21:21:32 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/reference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reference - Statistics and Probability</title>
      <link>/2021/07/03/reference-statistics-and-probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jul 2021 21:21:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/07/03/reference-statistics-and-probability/</guid>
      <description>CHANGES
Background This page is a refresher. Someone, may have studied statistics long ago and is in need of a reference.
This page borrows quite heavily from the MIT Statistics Cheat Sheet
Population: The entire group one desires information about Sample: A subset of the population taken because the entire population is usually too large to analyze; Its characteristics are taken to be representative of the population Mean: (average); The sum of all values in the sample divided by the number of values in the sample; $\mu$ = population mean $\overline{x}$ = sample mean Median: the value separating the higher half of a sample/population from lower half It is the middle value when all values arranged lowest to highest (or avg of middle two if even number of items) IQR: the middle 50%, calculated as Q3 - Q1 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reference - Linear Algebra</title>
      <link>/2021/06/27/reference-linear-algebra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 14:29:01 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/06/27/reference-linear-algebra/</guid>
      <description>Background This page is a refresher. The impetus for this page was a reference for someone who learned linear algebra in the past, but is in need of a refresher.
This page borrows very heavily from the excellent document Linear algebra explained in four pages by Ivan Savov.
Introduction Linear algebra is essentially the mathematics of vectors and matrices, so we start with a few definitions.
Vector: A vector $\overrightarrow{v} \in R^n$ is an $n$-tuple of real numbers $$ \overrightarrow{v}=(v_1,v_2,v_3) \in (R, R, R) \equiv R^{3} $$</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
