<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>John E. Freund&#39;s Mathematical Statistics with Applications - Miller/Miller on jrem.me - wonder.explore.share</title>
    <link>/categories/john-e.-freunds-mathematical-statistics-with-applications-miller/miller/</link>
    <description>Recent content in John E. Freund&#39;s Mathematical Statistics with Applications - Miller/Miller on jrem.me - wonder.explore.share</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="/categories/john-e.-freunds-mathematical-statistics-with-applications-miller/miller/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 4 - Mathematical Expectation</title>
      <link>/2022/08/30/chapter-4-mathematical-expectation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/08/30/chapter-4-mathematical-expectation/</guid>
      <description>4.1 Introduction Mathematical Expectation - Idea arising from games; the product of the amount a player stands to win and the probability that he or she will win
4.2 The Expected Value of a Random Variable Expected Value - If \(X\) is a discrete random variable and \(f(x)\) is the value of its probability distribution at \(x\), the expected value of \(X\) is
\[ E(X)= \underset{x} \sum x \cdot f(x) \]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 5 - Special Probability Distributions</title>
      <link>/2022/08/29/chapter-5-special-probability-distributions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/08/29/chapter-5-special-probability-distributions/</guid>
      <description>5.1 Introduction parameters - quantities that are constants for particular distributions, but can take on different values for different members of famiiles of distributions of the same kind
5.2 The Discrete Uniform Distribution Discrete Uniform Distribution - A random variable \(X\) has a discrete uniform distribution and it is referred to as a discrete uniform random variable if and only if it probability distribution is given by
\[ f(x) = \frac{1}{k} \; \text{for} \, x = x_1, x_2, \dots, x_k \]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 3 - Probability Distributions and Probability Densities</title>
      <link>/2022/08/28/chapter-3-probability-distributions-and-probability-densities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/08/28/chapter-3-probability-distributions-and-probability-densities/</guid>
      <description>3.1 Random Variables Random Variable - If \(S\) is a sample space with a probability measure and \(X\) is a real-valued function defined over the elements of \(S\), then \(X\) is called a random variable
Discrete Random Variables - random variables whose range is finite or countably infinite
3.2 Probability Distributions Probability Distribution - If \(X\) is a discrete random variable, the function given by \(f(x)=P(X=x)\) for each \(x\) within the range of \(X\) is called the probability distribution of \(X\)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 1 - Introduction</title>
      <link>/2022/08/27/chapter-1-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/08/27/chapter-1-introduction/</guid>
      <description>1.2 Combinatorial Methods Theorem 1.1 [2-steps] If an operation consists of two steps, of which the first can be done in \(n_1\) ways and for each of these the second can be done in \(n_2\) ways, then the whole operation can be done in \(n_1 \cdot n_2\) ways.
Theorem 1.2 [k-steps] If an operation consists of \(k\) steps, of which the first can be done in \(n_1\) ways, for each of these the second step can be done in \(n_2\) ways, for each of the first two the third step can be done in \(n_3\) ways, and so forth, then the whole operation can be done in \(n_1 \cdot n_2 \cdot \ldots \cdot n_k\) ways.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chapter 2 - Probability</title>
      <link>/2022/08/27/chapter-2-probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/08/27/chapter-2-probability/</guid>
      <description>2.1 Introduction Classical Probability Concept - If there are \(N\) equally likely possibilities, of which one must occur and \(n\) are regarded as favorable, or as a “success” then the probability of a “success” is given by the ratio \(\frac{n}{N}\)
Frequency Interpretation - The probability of an event (outcome or happening) is the proportion of the time that events of the same kind will occur in the long run</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
